<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: London | Mein(un)sinn]]></title>
  <link href="http://Velrok.github.io/blog/categories/london/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://Velrok.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-27T20:57:49+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://Velrok.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[velrok]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Developers Love Bacon - Conference]]></title>
    <link href="http://Velrok.github.io/blog/2014/05/17/developers-love-bacon-conference/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-17T14:45:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://Velrok.github.io/blog/2014/05/17/developers-love-bacon-conference</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/bacon_2014.png" alt="bacon" /></p>

<blockquote><p>BACON is a two-day conference on all the things developers love.</p></blockquote>

<p>And that is exactly what it is. A friendly get together of people that like to code
and other things they are interested in.
All talks are limited to 30 min and come in a huge variety.
Thus the talks are more about general inspiration than about hard facts.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Due to the fact, that the conference runs two
tracks in parallel I could only attend about half of the talks.</p>

<h2>My Highlights</h2>

<p><a href="http://devslovebacon.com/conferences/bacon-2014/talks/from-colo-to-yolo-confessions-of-the-angriest-archivist">FROM COLO TO YOLO: CONFESSIONS OF THE ANGRIEST ARCHIVIST</a></p>

<p><a href="http://ascii.textfiles.com/">Jason Scott</a>,
was probably the most entertaining and passionate speaker at the conf.
What starts out a bit wired and arty progresses into a talk that conveys his passion
for saving the cultural data that is hosted and bound inside all the new shiny
online services (instagram for cats anyone?).
Specially in cases where all the data is about to permanently to disappear, with
30 days notice.</p>

<p><a href="http://devslovebacon.com/conferences/bacon-2014/talks/coding-and-the-mozart-effect">CODING AND THE MOZART EFFECT</a></p>

<p>Everyone likes music. So does <a href="@aspleenic">PJ Hagerty</a>.
Given the right mix you can increase your concentration and get cleverer, at least for a couple of
minutes / hours.
Watch PJs talk for more information and a great presentation of what is possible
with music and how you can get new listening material that is both new and
interesting.</p>

<p><a href="http://devslovebacon.com/conferences/bacon-2014/talks/living-with-ocd">LIVING WITH OCD</a></p>

<p><a href="https://sethvargo.com">Seth Vargo</a> has a condition. While his OCD can drive him crazy during a normal day
out and about, he found that it also comes in handy in his job as a Dev and also
makes him ridiculously efficient when it comes to shopping.
This talk gives a delightful view into a very orderly mind and makes a point
that you can live your life with OCD.</p>

<p><a href="http://devslovebacon.com/conferences/bacon-2014/talks/there-is-no-such-thing-as-work-life-balance-working-with-burnout">THERE IS NO SUCH THING AS WORK-LIFE BALANCE (WORKING WITH BURNOUT)</a></p>

<p><a href="http://adamonishi.com">Adam Onishi</a> talks about having Burnout.
I learned that it is not something that happens to you, but a tendency of overworking yourself,
which will happen again if you are not careful.
Apparently a strong intrinsic motivation, which lets you accomplish great things,
is also the reason why you overwork yourself.
A very personal talk.</p>

<p><a href="http://devslovebacon.com/conferences/bacon-2014/talks/whisk-e-y-the-best-drink-in-the-world">WHISK(E)Y: THE BEST DRINK IN THE WORLD</a></p>

<p>At the bacon is somewhat famous for having at least one talk about booze :).
While you will not be able to take part in the wisky
tasting <a href="http://www.billyabbott.co.uk/home/">Billy Abbott</a> still holes an interesting talk about the process of actually creating
the spirit. Did you know that it is basically distilled beer?</p>

<p><a href="http://devslovebacon.com/conferences/bacon-2014/talks/sweaty-horse-blanket-processing-the-natural-language-of-beer">SWEATY HORSE BLANKET - PROCESSING THE NATURAL LANGUAGE OF BEER</a></p>

<p>Being a bit overwhelmed with the sheer about of choice of beer in Londoner pubs,
<a href="http://benfields.net">Ben Fields</a> sets out to apply Natural language processing (NLP) to tackle the problem.
Another highly informative and very entertaining talk.
Obviously one can not teach the math behind things like
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Latent_Dirichlet_allocation">Latent Dirichlet allocation (LDA)</a>
in a 30 min. talk, but he manages to give the gist across and just show what is
possible with a bunch of text and an understanding of a domain.</p>

<p><a href="http://devslovebacon.com/conferences/bacon-2014/talks/your-web-stack-would-betray-you-in-an-instant">YOUR WEB STACK WOULD BETRAY YOU IN AN INSTANT</a></p>

<p>Security is a tricky thing. <a href="https://github.com/pimterry">Tim Perry</a> reiterates some exemplary incidents of
different parts of the web stack in a funny well structured way.
He also reminds us that best practices are best practices for a reason and that
many of the incidents could have been avoided if people would run the test they have
and read their bug trackers.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>I really liked the <a href="http://devslovebacon.com/">Bacon 2014</a> for its lineup of
interesting talk about all kind of things.
You will probably not experience an scientific talk about implementation details
or the latest distributed algorithm, but chances are you stumble across a talk
that sparks an interest in
<a href="http://devslovebacon.com/conferences/bacon-2014/talks/whisk-e-y-the-best-drink-in-the-world">Wisky</a>,
<a href="http://devslovebacon.com/conferences/bacon-2014/talks/the-joy-of-blink-dot-ino-shining-a-light-on-working-with-hardware">Arduino programming</a>
or even
<a href="http://devslovebacon.com/conferences/bacon-2014/talks/the-benefits-of-powerlifting-for-the-desk-bound-geek">Powerlifting</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Moving to London: Banks and Money]]></title>
    <link href="http://Velrok.github.io/blog/2014/01/26/moving-to-london-banks-and-money/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-26T15:05:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://Velrok.github.io/blog/2014/01/26/moving-to-london-banks-and-money</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/money.jpg" alt="money" /></p>

<p>I moved to London two days ago to start my new job here.
So this is an attempt to collect information and sources that I found useful.
This article is specifically about Money and basic Banking stuff.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Choosing a bank account for your income</h2>

<p>When you are working in the UK chances are that your employer requires a UK
bank account that holds your money in Pounds.
"Current Account" is the technical term for an account that is designed to
collect your income and pay your bills.
I used <a href="http://www.moneysupermarket.com/current-accounts/search/results/?goal=CUR_INTEREST">money super market</a>
to find an account suitable to my needs.
They have good how-tos that cover the basics without being lengthy.</p>

<p>You want to start this early, about 2-3 weeks before you move to the UK.
This way your account is already set up and you can wire money into it, which
can take days.
I missed that and had to hustle with different account debit card limits and
long money transaction times.
As soon as you arrive you want to make an appointment to be authenticated.
This will require you to turn up in person at a branch of the bank with your
passport.
Only after you have been authenticated can you withdraw money from your new
account.</p>

<p>You might get only a standard migrant account, since you will not have a local
address yet.
The account you have chosen online will only be available once you can provide
a credit score and a local address.</p>

<h2>Moving money between the UK and your homeland</h2>

<p>The Current Account might be your primary account for any money business inside
the UK but if you want to transfer money to a different country it will probably
get very expensive, because they might charge you as much as 30£ for each transfer.
They might also give you a slightly worse conversion rate, compared to what
is possible.</p>

<p>However there are money transfer institutions that specialize in moving money
to different currencies.
I used <a href="http://www.money.co.uk/money-transfers/money-transfer-to-germany.htm">money.co.uk</a>
to get a list of institutions to choose from.
Again which is the best depends on your circumstances, do you transfer money
frequently, do you have to transfer large amounts and so forth.
<a href="http://www.money.co.uk/money-transfers/money-transfer-to-germany.htm">money.co.uk</a>
helped me to find a good fit for my needs (many low amount transactions
to my private pension found).</p>

<h3>bitcoin as an alternative?</h3>

<p>If you only want to make a few transactions, and want to circumvent the cross
country fees, you could try to use a crypto currency like
<a href="http://www.coindesk.com/information/what-is-bitcoin/">Bitcoin</a> as an
intermediary currency.
I found <a href="http://www.coindesk.com/">CoinDesk</a> to be comprehensible.
However at this point this is just an idea I might try in the next days / weeks.</p>

<h2>Feedback</h2>

<p>As I said I'm reporting to be best of my knowledge, which isn't much.
If I got something wrong or if you have any remarks please let me
know, in the comments.
If this article help you I'm also happy for any shout out or comment.</p>

<p>Let me know what you think!</p>

<h2>Disclaimer</h2>

<p>Everything written is my personal experience.
I'm not an expert on this topics.</p>

<p>For now all of this is strictly theoretical. As of this writing I have not
signed any contract, because it is a Sunday and all institutions are closed.
Should anything turn out to be totally off or different I will post an update.</p>

<p>I do not receive any money from any of the mentions websites or institutions.</p>

<p>I'm writing this disclaimer just because if came to me :).
I have no idea what I'm doing ;) .
Think for yourself ;P.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
